[Music]
Professor Dave and CH here we know that
alkanes are fully saturated hydrocarbons
meaning they possess the maximum
hydrogen content possible so every
carbon has as many bonds to hydrogen as
possible but some hydrocarbons are
unsaturated so let's learn about the
various degrees of unsaturation that are
possible if sat saturation means maximum
possible hydrogen content then
unsaturation means less than the maximum
possible hydrogen content in other words
carbon atoms are participating in
additional carboncarbon bonds or bonds
to other elements instead of bonding to
hydrogen so ethane c2h6 is fully
saturated because the two carbon atoms
can't have any more bonds to hydrogen
atoms ethine or ethylene c2h4 has one
degree of unsaturation due to the carbon
carbon Pi bond this Pi bond is
preventing two additional hydrogen atoms
from coordinating we can say the same
thing about straight chain butane or
c4h10 versus cyob butane or
c4h8 because the molecule closes in on
itself to form a ring the two end
carbons must have a bond between them
and this additional Bond results in a
degree of unsaturation in general every
Pi Bond and ring in a molecule adds
another degree of unsaturation which
will result in two hydrogens lost from
the maximum possible given by cnh h2n +2
which describes alkanes knowing the
degree of unsaturation can help us
predict molecular structure let's say
that we know the molecular mass of a
hydrocarbon as being 82 atomic mass
units which corresponds with a formula
of C6 h10 if a six carbon molecule were
fully Satur saturated it would have the
formula C6 h14 since there are only 10
hydrogens this molecule must have 2° of
unsaturation this does not tell us
precisely what the molecule is but we
know that the molecule must either have
two piie bonds two rings or one Pi Bond
and one ring so it could be
cyclohexene it could be hexine or many
other possibilities degrees of
unsaturation can extend to compounds
with hetero atoms as well for more
involved examples we will use this
equation instead where the number of
degrees of unsaturation will be equal to
twice the number of carbon atoms in the
molecule plus two plus the number of
nitrogen atoms minus the number of
halogens minus the number of hydrogens
all over two so for example take the
formula C6 h10 NCL how many degrees of
unsaturation must this molecule have
well twice the number of carbons is 12
plus 2 plus the one nitrogen minus the
one hogen minus 10 hydrogens all over
two so that's 4 over 2 which is equal to
two and in fact this could be a molecule
like this and with the one ring and the
one Pi Bond we do indeed see that there
are two degrees of
unsaturation this concept of degrees of
unsaturation will be useful for certain
applications especially spect R roscopy
which we will examine later for now we
must simply know what this term means
and be able to determine molecules which
exhibit a specific number of degrees of
unsaturation Professor Dave for check
see you next
time